<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Community on Brookline Compliance With The MBTA Community Act</title>
    <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/categories/community/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Community on Brookline Compliance With The MBTA Community Act</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 28 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/categories/community/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>How do we balance the rights of people to do what they want with their property and the rights of residents to be able to control the character of their neighborhoods?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/liberty-vs-community/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/liberty-vs-community/</guid>
      <description>Balancing the rights of property owners with community standards is the work of democracy. Involvement of citizens, experts and legislatures is crucial.
Many committees and departments are involved in crafting zoning by-laws that balance these needs, including the following:
Select Board Advisory Committee (to review Warrant Articles) Advisory Subcommittee on Land Use Planning Department of Planning and Community Development Planning Board Preservation Commission Select Board Multifamily Planning Committee Town Counsel Town Meeting </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How can we keep our commercial districts like Coolidge Corner viable and still be compliant with the MBTA-CA?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/protecting-commercial-use/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/protecting-commercial-use/</guid>
      <description>Form-based zoning can help us comply with the MBTA-CA. By specifying form-based zoning by-laws, we can constrain the buildings that are multi-family as of right to dramatically favor the maintenance and creation of first-floor retail. For example, making the first floor at ground level and have its frontage be 80% transparent. The Economic Development Advisory Board and the Housing Advisory Board are working on a proposal to provide developer relief for commercial retail.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What kinds of zoning would assuage the concerns of abutters to mixed use or multi-family buildings on Harvard St?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/harvard-study/abutter-concerns/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/harvard-study/abutter-concerns/</guid>
      <description>Form-based Zoning Form-based zoning can require or prohibit specific elements of buildings that are out of character with a neighborhood or impinge on abutting neighborhoods. For example, concerns about sky-view would be addressed by step-backs on the top floor. The step-backs could be different for areas that abut single-family, 2-family or 3-family zones.
Process Without a special permit, the zoning by-laws can nonetheless specify that projects be subjected to a planning review by the planning board.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What ways besides form-based zoning can address concerns of abutters?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/other-solutions-to-abutter-concerns/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/other-solutions-to-abutter-concerns/</guid>
      <description>Curb control: As projects are permitted and reviewed by the planning department, loading zones can be specified for those projects. Then you can get the developer to pay for the installation of the zone. If there is no pending project, DPW can prioritize it as part of the strategic plan.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>If we don’t mandate commercial use, what will happen to all of the stores in Coolidge Corner?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/coolidge-corner-without-commercial-mandate/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/coolidge-corner-without-commercial-mandate/</guid>
      <description>If we implement form-based zoning, even without a mandate for ground-floor commercial use, we can incentivize ground floor retail so strongly that it won&amp;rsquo;t be economically reasonable for property owners to eliminate existing ground-floor retail.
What is the difference between form-based zoning and conventional zoning?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>If we eliminate parking minimums, where will people who buy units without parking park?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/parking-without-minimums/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/parking-without-minimums/</guid>
      <description>Most developers opt to provide parking on site to meet market demand, as Brookline has a strict on-street parking bylaw, which precludes spill over parking in the public way for residents.
The proposed zoning for Harvard Street would set a parking maximum of 1 parking space per dwelling unit. Based on parking data by census tract, 1 parking space is more than enough space to meet demand.
40B developers on Harvard Street have been granted waivers to provide 0.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How much will the mandate of zoning 6990 units burden our schools and other town services?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/burden-on-town-services/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/burden-on-town-services/</guid>
      <description>The MBTA-CA Act and guidelines require zoning changes, not a building plan, so the zoning changes themselves won&amp;rsquo;t add to the cost of providing town services, including education.
The cost of providing services for new residents is offset by the property tax revenue generated by the housing for those new residents.
Different residents of Brookline make use of different services. Senior citizens and families with school age children may have different needs, and the town can balance budgets and services as needed.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
