<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Harvard Street Zoning Proposal on Brookline Compliance With The MBTA Community Act</title>
    <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/categories/harvard-street-zoning-proposal/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Harvard Street Zoning Proposal on Brookline Compliance With The MBTA Community Act</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/categories/harvard-street-zoning-proposal/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>What might the Harvard Street proposal accomplish besides MBTA-CA compliance?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/harvard-study/benefits/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/harvard-study/benefits/</guid>
      <description>In addition to MBTA-CA compliance, the Harvard Street proposal could provide the following benefits:
more residents using our biggest retail corridor more predictable development in line with community standards more affordable housing, well integrated into our housing inventory, instead of 40B projects that we are being forced to accept. </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How many units of housing will be incentivized by the Harvard St plan?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/harvard-street-incentivized-units/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/harvard-street-incentivized-units/</guid>
      <description>The Harvard Street zoning proposal doesn&amp;rsquo;t have a production goal.
However, looking at 1 and 2 story retail building, between 800 and 1200 units of infill are available across the Harvard St Study area. The incentives to redevelop 2 story buildings are low because of the revenue lost during the construction project. Just looking at 1 story retail buildings, the number is closer to 800 units.
If you ask to property owners whether they would redevelop, some say &amp;ldquo;I might do it for 6 stories, probably not for 4&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;if I could buy the abutting lot, then it might be feasible to redevelop.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
