<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Brookline Compliance With The MBTA Community Act</title>
    <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Brookline Compliance With The MBTA Community Act</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 10 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>What is the MBTA Community Act?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/the-law/mbta-community-act/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/the-law/mbta-community-act/</guid>
      <description>The MBTA Community Act is a bill that was passed into law in Massachusetts. It requires zoning changes to allow multi-family housing as of right in the 175 communities that are served by the MBTA.
The law is in General Laws, Part I, Title VII, Chapter 40A, Section 3A.
What does the MBTA-CA require that the Town of Brookline do?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What does the MBTA-CA require that the Town of Brookline do?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/the-law/mbtaca-requirements/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/the-law/mbtaca-requirements/</guid>
      <description>Because Brookline is a &amp;ldquo;rapid transit community&amp;rdquo; (i.e., it has sufficient developable land close to the Green Line B, C and D branches), the town must submit a plan to be approved by the Executive Office of Housing and Livable Communities (EOHLC) by December 31st, 2023.
EOHLC has published final compliance guidelines with which the plan Brookline submits must comply.
Because the plan will include changes to our zoning by-laws, the changes must be approved by Town Meeting at a special meeting in November, 2023.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is the impact of requiring Brookline to create a zoning district which allows multi-family-housing as of right?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/multi-family-housing-by-right/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/multi-family-housing-by-right/</guid>
      <description>The MBTA Community Act (MBTA-CA) and DHCD Guidelines require that all lots within a specified multi-family zoning district are permitted to build multi-family housing by right. Requiring a special permit for any reason is prohibited.
Risks of poorly specifying a multi-family zoning district include:
Ground floor shops, such as those in Coolidge Corner, might be replaced by expensive condos that are more profitable to build. Buildings might not meet aesthetic, size, safety, environmental or other standards of their neighborhoods.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is the difference between multi-family buildings and multi-use buildings?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/multi-family-vs-multi-use-buildings/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/multi-family-vs-multi-use-buildings/</guid>
      <description>A multi-use building combines multiple uses into the same building, such as residential and commercial, whereas a multi-family building contains only housing.
What is the impact of requiring Brookline to create a zoning district which allows multi-family-housing as of right?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What guidelines has the EOHLC published?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/eohlc-multi-family-housing-guidelines/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/eohlc-multi-family-housing-guidelines/</guid>
      <description>The EOHLC has published guidelines that describe how cities and towns must comply with the MBTA-CA.
For example, there are guidelines for allowing multi-family housing &#34;as of right&#34;
The following are examples of requirements that would be deemed to be inconsistent with “as of right” use: &amp;hellip;; and (iii) a requirement that multi-family use must be combined with commercial or other uses on the same lot or as part of a single project.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why can’t we require commercial use on the first floor of building on Harvard Street and remain compliant with the MBTA-CA?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/mbtaca-prohibits-requiring-commercial-use/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/mbtaca-prohibits-requiring-commercial-use/</guid>
      <description>If a zoning by-law requires commercial use in any part of a building, that building becomes a multi-use building, not a multi-family building. Because the MBTA Community Act (MBTA-CA) requires that all lots within a compliant multi-family zoning district are permitted to build multi-family housing by right, this requirement makes the area being zoned non-compliant with the MBTA.
A zoning by-law can allow multi-use buildings as well as multi-family buildings and be compliant; the by-law cannot require multi-use or commercial building.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What are the requirements that Brookline zoning by-laws must meet to be compliant with the MBTA-CA?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/brookline-zoning-by-law-requirements/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/brookline-zoning-by-law-requirements/</guid>
      <description>Brookline must designate a land area of at least 41 acres that allow multi-family housing by right, known as its &amp;ldquo;multi-family zoning district&amp;rdquo;. The district must have a theoretical capacity of 6,990 units of housing.
At least 50% of the district must be comprised of contiguous lots. Each part of the district must be at least 5 acres of contiguous lots.
90% of the district must be within 0.5 miles of an MBTA subway station, commuter rail station, ferry terminal or bus station.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is the town doing to comply with the MBTA-CA?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/mbtaca-compliance-activity/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/mbtaca-compliance-activity/</guid>
      <description>The town is proceeding in two ways:
The Planning department is developing a zoning update for Harvard Street. The Select Board has charged the MBTA-CA Multifamily Permitting Committee with exploring other options. The Planning Department&#39;s web page devoted to this project answers this question in detail.
What does the MBTA-CA require that the Town of Brookline do?
What goals does the town have besides compliance with the MBTA-CA?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What goals does the town have besides compliance with the MBTA-CA?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/goals-of-the-town/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/goals-of-the-town/</guid>
      <description>The following Goals of the Town were approved in a Select Board Resolution on February 7, 2023.
Protect and expand Commercial uses and commercial tax base Increase net amount of nonluxury housing suitable for all stages of life Facilitate racial, ethnic, income diversity The number of units likely to be built in the multi-family zoning district should be at least 699 units. That is 10% of the capacity required to comply with the MBTA-CA.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Where does the goal for the number of likely units come from?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/town-likely-to-build-housing-goal/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/town-likely-to-build-housing-goal/</guid>
      <description>The MBTA Community Act does not require any housing to be built. It only requires zoning to allow sufficient multi-family housing in a compliant zoning district.
However, the Select Board’s charge to the MBTA-CA Multifamily Permitting Committee includes developing a plan to create at least 699 units, 10% of the total capacity required in Brookline’s MBTA-CA compliant zoning district.
How many units of housing will be incentivized by the Harvard St plan?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What’s wrong with our current zoning code aside from a lack of compliance with MBTA-CA?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/current-zoning-bylaw-problems/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/current-zoning-bylaw-problems/</guid>
      <description>Our current zoning code frequently using FAR to determine the maximum size of a building on a lot. However, using the FAR doesn&amp;rsquo;t lead to predictable outcomes for the form of a building.
The extensive use of special permits in our zoning code make developing housing more expensive because the permitting process takes longer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How would we integrate some elements of the Harvard St study into any proposal that was developed by the Select Board Multifamily Planning Committee?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/harvard-study/integrating-into-other-plans/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/harvard-study/integrating-into-other-plans/</guid>
      <description>Who would be responsible for that integration?
This isn&amp;rsquo;t part of the remit of the Harvard Street Proposal for MBTA Compliance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What happens if Brookline fails to comply with the MBTA-CA?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/failure-to-comply/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/failure-to-comply/</guid>
      <description>The Attorney General has stated publicly that towns that do not comply with the MBTA, in addition to losing access to state funding for public housing, will be sued by the state.
According to my conversations with the Town Counsel the following would likely occur:
In January, the lawsuit would probably be filed and Brookline would lose through a summary judgement. Brookline would be given a period of time, such as 90 days, to comply.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why shouldn&#39;t communities that are less dense than Brookline have to take a bigger share of the burden?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/fair-share-concerns/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/fair-share-concerns/</guid>
      <description>Compliance with the MBTA-CA Guidelines uses a theoretical capacity to determine the minimum number of units in a compliant zoning district. This theoretical capacity is calculcated as if each parcel of land has no building on it.
Since Brookline’s compliant zoning district is more likely to have buildings in it already, the burden to build additional housing on Brookline could actually be relatively lower than other, less dense communities.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Will MBTA-CA compliance create affordable housing in Brookline?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/mbtaca-affordable-housing-impact/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/mbtaca-affordable-housing-impact/</guid>
      <description>Compliance with the MBTA-CA requires changes to zoning. It is not a housing production plan, so it doesn&amp;rsquo;t automatically create any housing, affordable or not.
Since Warrant Article 14 passed, Brookline has a requirement town-wide that multi-family housing with more than 10 units will have to have 15% of their units deed affordable. Any housing created in the multi-family zoning district will have to comply with this zoning by-law.
The Select Board has established goals for the town for our MBTA compliance that include that there will be at least 699 units of housing likely to be built in the multi-family zoning district.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What incentives provide relief for developers if they add affordable housing to their buildings?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/harvard-study/developer-relief-for-commercial-retail/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/harvard-study/developer-relief-for-commercial-retail/</guid>
      <description>In certain locations, the best economic use of the ground floor will be commercial, because owners can get higher rents from commercial leases than residential leases. Normally, these buildings will be four stories high, and 15% of the units must be deemed affordable to lower income people.
However, since people with middle incomes need affordable housing as well, Brookline can incentivize middle income housing, such as units affordable to residents at 80% of the Area Median Income (AMI) alongside the purely economic incentives for ground floor commercial.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How do we balance the rights of people to do what they want with their property and the rights of residents to be able to control the character of their neighborhoods?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/liberty-vs-community/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/liberty-vs-community/</guid>
      <description>Balancing the rights of property owners with community standards is the work of democracy. Involvement of citizens, experts and legislatures is crucial.
Many committees and departments are involved in crafting zoning by-laws that balance these needs, including the following:
Select Board Advisory Committee (to review Warrant Articles) Advisory Subcommittee on Land Use Planning Department of Planning and Community Development Planning Board Preservation Commission Select Board Multifamily Planning Committee Town Counsel Town Meeting </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How can we keep our commercial districts like Coolidge Corner viable and still be compliant with the MBTA-CA?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/protecting-commercial-use/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/protecting-commercial-use/</guid>
      <description>Form-based zoning can help us comply with the MBTA-CA. By specifying form-based zoning by-laws, we can constrain the buildings that are multi-family as of right to dramatically favor the maintenance and creation of first-floor retail. For example, making the first floor at ground level and have its frontage be 80% transparent. The Economic Development Advisory Board and the Housing Advisory Board are working on a proposal to provide developer relief for commercial retail.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What kinds of zoning would assuage the concerns of abutters to mixed use or multi-family buildings on Harvard St?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/harvard-study/abutter-concerns/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/harvard-study/abutter-concerns/</guid>
      <description>Form-based Zoning Form-based zoning can require or prohibit specific elements of buildings that are out of character with a neighborhood or impinge on abutting neighborhoods. For example, concerns about sky-view would be addressed by step-backs on the top floor. The step-backs could be different for areas that abut single-family, 2-family or 3-family zones.
Process Without a special permit, the zoning by-laws can nonetheless specify that projects be subjected to a planning review by the planning board.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What ways besides form-based zoning can address concerns of abutters?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/other-solutions-to-abutter-concerns/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/other-solutions-to-abutter-concerns/</guid>
      <description>Curb control: As projects are permitted and reviewed by the planning department, loading zones can be specified for those projects. Then you can get the developer to pay for the installation of the zone. If there is no pending project, DPW can prioritize it as part of the strategic plan.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>If we don’t mandate commercial use, what will happen to all of the stores in Coolidge Corner?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/coolidge-corner-without-commercial-mandate/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/coolidge-corner-without-commercial-mandate/</guid>
      <description>If we implement form-based zoning, even without a mandate for ground-floor commercial use, we can incentivize ground floor retail so strongly that it won&amp;rsquo;t be economically reasonable for property owners to eliminate existing ground-floor retail.
What is the difference between form-based zoning and conventional zoning?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>If we eliminate parking minimums, where will people who buy units without parking park?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/parking-without-minimums/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/parking-without-minimums/</guid>
      <description>Most developers opt to provide parking on site to meet market demand, as Brookline has a strict on-street parking bylaw, which precludes spill over parking in the public way for residents.
The proposed zoning for Harvard Street would set a parking maximum of 1 parking space per dwelling unit. Based on parking data by census tract, 1 parking space is more than enough space to meet demand.
40B developers on Harvard Street have been granted waivers to provide 0.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How much will the mandate of zoning 6990 units burden our schools and other town services?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/burden-on-town-services/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/burden-on-town-services/</guid>
      <description>The MBTA-CA Act and guidelines require zoning changes, not a building plan, so the zoning changes themselves won&amp;rsquo;t add to the cost of providing town services, including education.
The cost of providing services for new residents is offset by the property tax revenue generated by the housing for those new residents.
Different residents of Brookline make use of different services. Senior citizens and families with school age children may have different needs, and the town can balance budgets and services as needed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How will form-based zoning help us comply with the MBTA-CA?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/advantages-of-form-based-zoning/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/advantages-of-form-based-zoning/</guid>
      <description>Form-based zoning by-laws are specific, measurable and defensible. With form-based zoning, we will have predictable building projects that meet the characteristics of their neighborhoods without needing to require a special permit.
There are several categories of form-based zoning.
By contrast, our current zoning by-laws use conventional zoning.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What kinds of zoning by-laws are form-based?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/form-based-zoning-categories/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/form-based-zoning-categories/</guid>
      <description>Form-based zoning can encompass many different types of requirements that are built into zoning by-laws. The common theme of form-based zoning is that all of the requirements are objective and measurable, not subjective.
Limitations specified in form-based zoning can be relaxed for specific areas by creating an overlay district.
Schematic Massing By-laws that ensure that the mass of a building is in scale with other buildings in its neighborhood.
Maximum building heights Minimum or maximum floor heights Step-backs from one floor to the next Set-backs from the edge of lots Character/architectural Style By-laws that ensure that the character and style of a building are coherent with other buildings in its neighborhood.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is the difference between form-based zoning and conventional zoning?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/form-based-vs-conventional-zoning/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/form-based-vs-conventional-zoning/</guid>
      <description>Form-based zoning describes precise measurable requirements for the forms of buildings and their surrounding, whereas conventional zoning defines some measurable limits that can lead to a variety of different forms for buildings and their surroundings.
For example, conventional zoning might specify a Floor-Area Ratio, which can lead to buildings with dramatically different shapes (a building with one floor of 5000 square feet and a building with five floors of 1000 square feet would both have the same floor area).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Are there design principles or urban planning principles which would help specify how parking was or wasn&#39;t integrated into the form based zoning by-laws?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/harvard-study/parking-concerns/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/harvard-study/parking-concerns/</guid>
      <description>The current zoning by-laws have no meaningful parameters for parking, such as where it is located.
We want design guidelines built into our zoning that are conducive to successful retail. Active ground floor design guidelines conducive to retail could include:
No parking along the front of a lot No curb cuts on Harvard St (eats up parking and pedestrian safety) No parking entrance visible within 50% of the front of the lot.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Where are the design standards for Multi-family districts if we remove special permit requirements to comply with MBTA-CA?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/m-district-design-standards/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/m-district-design-standards/</guid>
      <description>This question will need to be answered by the Select Board Multifamily Permitting Committee.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Would form-based zoning ideas transfer to areas of Beacon St that are potentially under-developed, such as St. Mary&#39;s, Summit Ave and Washington Square?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/form-based-zoning-for-beacon-st-areas/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/form-based-zoning-for-beacon-st-areas/</guid>
      <description>Could this be done in time to include those areas in the alternative plan being developed by the Select Board Multifamily Planning Committee?
Those are deeper lots with different parameters for the footprints. Especially with Beacon St.,
Can re-use the experience, but not the particular results. For example&amp;hellip;
Standards for areas in the front yard at St. Mary&amp;rsquo;s. What about fore-courts (need zoning for that) Haven&amp;rsquo;t studied the adjacency there. Also grade changes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What might the Harvard Street proposal accomplish besides MBTA-CA compliance?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/harvard-study/benefits/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/harvard-study/benefits/</guid>
      <description>In addition to MBTA-CA compliance, the Harvard Street proposal could provide the following benefits:
more residents using our biggest retail corridor more predictable development in line with community standards more affordable housing, well integrated into our housing inventory, instead of 40B projects that we are being forced to accept. </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How many units of housing will be incentivized by the Harvard St plan?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/harvard-street-incentivized-units/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/harvard-street-incentivized-units/</guid>
      <description>The Harvard Street zoning proposal doesn&amp;rsquo;t have a production goal.
However, looking at 1 and 2 story retail building, between 800 and 1200 units of infill are available across the Harvard St Study area. The incentives to redevelop 2 story buildings are low because of the revenue lost during the construction project. Just looking at 1 story retail buildings, the number is closer to 800 units.
If you ask to property owners whether they would redevelop, some say &amp;ldquo;I might do it for 6 stories, probably not for 4&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;if I could buy the abutting lot, then it might be feasible to redevelop.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is 40B?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/40b/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/40b/</guid>
      <description>Chapter 40B of the Massachusetts General Law allows builders to bypass local zoning laws to create affordable housing in cities and town that do not meet a certain threshold.
For Brookline, the threshold is met when 10% of our housing is part of our Subsidized Housing Inventory maintained by the state.
40B Project</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is a 40B project?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/40b-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/40b-project/</guid>
      <description>A 40B project is a building that is permitted to be built according to Chapter 40B of the Massachusetts General Laws.
Chapter 40B projects are limited in how profitable they can be. However, 40B buildings can compensate for those limits by being larger than projects that follow local zoning laws.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What’s wrong with all of the 40B projects that are happening?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/40b-project-problems/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/40b-project-problems/</guid>
      <description>Developers of buildings use Chapter 40B to bypass town zoning by-laws. As a result, the town cannot ensure that such projects fit into their neighborhoods according to the wishes of the community.
What is Chapter 40B?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How can we prevent being forced to accept 40B projects?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/40b-project-threshold/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/40b-project-threshold/</guid>
      <description>Brookline can reject 40B applications from developers when the subsidized housing inventory of Brookline is above 10% of the total housing stock. When Brookline&amp;rsquo;s subsidized housing inventory is above that threshold, developers can not appeal such rejections.
Thus, to prevent us from bring forced to accept 40B projects, we would have to build or permit housing units that become part of our subsidized housing inventory to stay over the threshold.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>If we only change our zoning to comply with the MBTA-CA without incentivizing more housing, will we still be forced to accept 40B projects?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/mbtaca-40b-impact/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/mbtaca-40b-impact/</guid>
      <description>With our current zoning by-laws, the planning department projects that Brookline will fall below the 10% threshold for being able to reject 40B applications in September, 2023.
By implementing the Harvard Street Study, new developments on Harvard St will all be four story projects with 15% affordable units. This increases both the Numerator and the Denominator of the ratio used to determine if we have enough affordable housing to be able to reject Chapter 40B applications.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>15-minute community</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/15-minute-communities/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/15-minute-communities/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;Imagine a city where everything you needed could be found within a fifteen-minute walk or bike ride from your home, including fresh food, healthcare, schools, offices, shops, parks, gyms, banks, and diverse entertainment. The paths to get there are safe, tree-shaded, car-free neighborhoods where people can get to know each other.&amp;rdquo; - Regeneration by Paul Hawkens</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Capacity</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/capacity-use/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/capacity-use/</guid>
      <description>Three definitions of capacity affect considerations of Brookline&amp;rsquo;s MBTA-CA compliance. By default, capacity is calculated assuming that one unit of housing capacity requires 1000 square feet, slightly greater than the size of a typical two-bedroom apartment.
Theoretical capacity is the number of units that could be built on a parcel if it were empty. EOHLC uses theoretical capacity to determine compliance.
Incremental capacity subtracts the floor area of what is already built from the theoretical capacity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>EOHLC</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/eohlc/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/eohlc/</guid>
      <description>The Executive Office of Housing and Livable Communities is a cabinet level office that is charged with creating more homes in Massachusetts and lowering housing costs for residents. It was previously known as the Department of Housing and Community Development.
EOHLC enforces the MBTA-Communities Act by reviewing the plans from MBTA communities and determines whether those plans are in compliance with the MBTA-CA.
EOHLC has developed guidelines that specify what cities and towns need to do to comply with the MBTA-CA.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inclusionary Zoning</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/inclusionary-zoning/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/inclusionary-zoning/</guid>
      <description>Inclusionary zoning by-laws require developers to either include affordable units in their buildings or pay into a trust that develops affordable housing.
Payments made for inclusionary zoning go to the Affordable Housing Trust Fund.
In May, 2023, Town meeting passed Warrant Article 14. As a result, buildings with at least 11 housing units must include affordable housing on site.
According to state law, Brookline can&amp;rsquo;t require more than 10% of units for a building be affordable for residents at 80% of the area median income (AMI).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multi-Family Housing</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/the-law/multi-family-housing/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/the-law/multi-family-housing/</guid>
      <description>According to the MBTA-CA, “Multi-family housing” means a building with 3 or more residential dwelling units or 2 or more buildings on the same lot with more than 1 residential dwelling unit in each building.
What is the impact of requiring that Brookline create a zoning district which allows Multi-Family Housing as of right?
MBTA-CA Guideline Definitions </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Overlay District</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/overlay-district/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/overlay-district/</guid>
      <description>An overlay district is an area of land that has zoning that can override the base zoning of the lots contained within the overlay district.
For example, if the base zoning of a certain type of district says that buildings cannot be taller than 45 feet, then overlay district zoning can allow buildings as tall as 55 feet within the overlay district.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Permitting As Of Right</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/permitting-by-right/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/permitting-by-right/</guid>
      <description>If a Zoning Bylaw says that a property can be used in a certain way &amp;ldquo;as of right&amp;rdquo;, then that means that the owner of the property doesn&amp;rsquo;t have to apply to the Zoning Board of Appeals to get a special permit to build on the property for that use.
What is the impact of requiring Brookline to create a zoning district which allows multi-family-housing as of right?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Special Permit</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/special-permit/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/special-permit/</guid>
      <description>A special permit is a permit issued by the Town Zoning Board of Appeals to allow a building to be built. The Zoning Board of Appeals has some discretion as to whether or not to issue a special permit, depending on the zoning code.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is Warrant Article 14 of the May, 2023 Annual Town Meeting?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/warrant-article-14/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/warrant-article-14/</guid>
      <description>Warrant Article 14 lowers the number of units that can be contained in a building before the building is required to contain affordable housing units. The current limit is 19 units and the proposed limit in warrant article 14 is 10 units.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
