<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>The Law on Brookline Compliance With The MBTA Community Act</title>
    <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/categories/the-law/</link>
    <description>Recent content in The Law on Brookline Compliance With The MBTA Community Act</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/categories/the-law/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>What is the MBTA Community Act?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/the-law/mbta-community-act/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/the-law/mbta-community-act/</guid>
      <description>The MBTA Community Act is a bill that was passed into law in Massachusetts. It requires zoning changes to allow multi-family housing as of right in the 175 communities that are served by the MBTA.
The law is in General Laws, Part I, Title VII, Chapter 40A, Section 3A.
What does the MBTA-CA require that the Town of Brookline do?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What does the MBTA-CA require that the Town of Brookline do?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/the-law/mbtaca-requirements/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/the-law/mbtaca-requirements/</guid>
      <description>Because Brookline is a &amp;ldquo;rapid transit community&amp;rdquo; (i.e., it has sufficient developable land close to the Green Line B, C and D branches), the town must submit a plan to be approved by the Executive Office of Housing and Livable Communities (EOHLC) by December 31st, 2023.
EOHLC has published final compliance guidelines with which the plan Brookline submits must comply.
Because the plan will include changes to our zoning by-laws, the changes must be approved by Town Meeting at a special meeting in November, 2023.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is the impact of requiring Brookline to create a zoning district which allows multi-family-housing as of right?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/multi-family-housing-by-right/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/multi-family-housing-by-right/</guid>
      <description>The MBTA Community Act (MBTA-CA) and DHCD Guidelines require that all lots within a specified multi-family zoning district are permitted to build multi-family housing by right. Requiring a special permit for any reason is prohibited.
Risks of poorly specifying a multi-family zoning district include:
Ground floor shops, such as those in Coolidge Corner, might be replaced by expensive condos that are more profitable to build. Buildings might not meet aesthetic, size, safety, environmental or other standards of their neighborhoods.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is the difference between multi-family buildings and multi-use buildings?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/multi-family-vs-multi-use-buildings/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/multi-family-vs-multi-use-buildings/</guid>
      <description>A multi-use building combines multiple uses into the same building, such as residential and commercial, whereas a multi-family building contains only housing.
What is the impact of requiring Brookline to create a zoning district which allows multi-family-housing as of right?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What guidelines has the EOHLC published?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/eohlc-multi-family-housing-guidelines/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/eohlc-multi-family-housing-guidelines/</guid>
      <description>The EOHLC has published guidelines that describe how cities and towns must comply with the MBTA-CA.
For example, there are guidelines for allowing multi-family housing &#34;as of right&#34;
The following are examples of requirements that would be deemed to be inconsistent with “as of right” use: &amp;hellip;; and (iii) a requirement that multi-family use must be combined with commercial or other uses on the same lot or as part of a single project.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why can’t we require commercial use on the first floor of building on Harvard Street and remain compliant with the MBTA-CA?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/mbtaca-prohibits-requiring-commercial-use/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/mbtaca-prohibits-requiring-commercial-use/</guid>
      <description>If a zoning by-law requires commercial use in any part of a building, that building becomes a multi-use building, not a multi-family building. Because the MBTA Community Act (MBTA-CA) requires that all lots within a compliant multi-family zoning district are permitted to build multi-family housing by right, this requirement makes the area being zoned non-compliant with the MBTA.
A zoning by-law can allow multi-use buildings as well as multi-family buildings and be compliant; the by-law cannot require multi-use or commercial building.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
