<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Form-based Zoning on Brookline Compliance With The MBTA Community Act</title>
    <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/categories/form-based-zoning/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Form-based Zoning on Brookline Compliance With The MBTA Community Act</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/categories/form-based-zoning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>How will form-based zoning help us comply with the MBTA-CA?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/advantages-of-form-based-zoning/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/advantages-of-form-based-zoning/</guid>
      <description>Form-based zoning by-laws are specific, measurable and defensible. With form-based zoning, we will have predictable building projects that meet the characteristics of their neighborhoods without needing to require a special permit.
There are several categories of form-based zoning.
By contrast, our current zoning by-laws use conventional zoning.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What kinds of zoning by-laws are form-based?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/form-based-zoning-categories/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/form-based-zoning-categories/</guid>
      <description>Form-based zoning can encompass many different types of requirements that are built into zoning by-laws. The common theme of form-based zoning is that all of the requirements are objective and measurable, not subjective.
Limitations specified in form-based zoning can be relaxed for specific areas by creating an overlay district.
Schematic Massing By-laws that ensure that the mass of a building is in scale with other buildings in its neighborhood.
Maximum building heights Minimum or maximum floor heights Step-backs from one floor to the next Set-backs from the edge of lots Character/architectural Style By-laws that ensure that the character and style of a building are coherent with other buildings in its neighborhood.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is the difference between form-based zoning and conventional zoning?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/form-based-vs-conventional-zoning/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/form-based-vs-conventional-zoning/</guid>
      <description>Form-based zoning describes precise measurable requirements for the forms of buildings and their surrounding, whereas conventional zoning defines some measurable limits that can lead to a variety of different forms for buildings and their surroundings.
For example, conventional zoning might specify a Floor-Area Ratio, which can lead to buildings with dramatically different shapes (a building with one floor of 5000 square feet and a building with five floors of 1000 square feet would both have the same floor area).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Are there design principles or urban planning principles which would help specify how parking was or wasn&#39;t integrated into the form based zoning by-laws?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/harvard-study/parking-concerns/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/harvard-study/parking-concerns/</guid>
      <description>The current zoning by-laws have no meaningful parameters for parking, such as where it is located.
We want design guidelines built into our zoning that are conducive to successful retail. Active ground floor design guidelines conducive to retail could include:
No parking along the front of a lot No curb cuts on Harvard St (eats up parking and pedestrian safety) No parking entrance visible within 50% of the front of the lot.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Where are the design standards for Multi-family districts if we remove special permit requirements to comply with MBTA-CA?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/m-district-design-standards/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/m-district-design-standards/</guid>
      <description>This question will need to be answered by the Select Board Multifamily Permitting Committee.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Would form-based zoning ideas transfer to areas of Beacon St that are potentially under-developed, such as St. Mary&#39;s, Summit Ave and Washington Square?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/form-based-zoning-for-beacon-st-areas/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/form-based-zoning-for-beacon-st-areas/</guid>
      <description>Could this be done in time to include those areas in the alternative plan being developed by the Select Board Multifamily Planning Committee?
Those are deeper lots with different parameters for the footprints. Especially with Beacon St.,
Can re-use the experience, but not the particular results. For example&amp;hellip;
Standards for areas in the front yard at St. Mary&amp;rsquo;s. What about fore-courts (need zoning for that) Haven&amp;rsquo;t studied the adjacency there. Also grade changes.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
