<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Affordability on Brookline Compliance With The MBTA Community Act</title>
    <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/categories/affordability/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Affordability on Brookline Compliance With The MBTA Community Act</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/categories/affordability/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Will MBTA-CA compliance create affordable housing in Brookline?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/mbtaca-affordable-housing-impact/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/mbtaca-affordable-housing-impact/</guid>
      <description>Compliance with the MBTA-CA requires changes to zoning. It is not a housing production plan, so it doesn&amp;rsquo;t automatically create any housing, affordable or not.
Since Warrant Article 14 passed, Brookline has a requirement town-wide that multi-family housing with more than 10 units will have to have 15% of their units deed affordable. Any housing created in the multi-family zoning district will have to comply with this zoning by-law.
The Select Board has established goals for the town for our MBTA compliance that include that there will be at least 699 units of housing likely to be built in the multi-family zoning district.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What incentives provide relief for developers if they add affordable housing to their buildings?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/harvard-study/developer-relief-for-commercial-retail/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/harvard-study/developer-relief-for-commercial-retail/</guid>
      <description>In certain locations, the best economic use of the ground floor will be commercial, because owners can get higher rents from commercial leases than residential leases. Normally, these buildings will be four stories high, and 15% of the units must be deemed affordable to lower income people.
However, since people with middle incomes need affordable housing as well, Brookline can incentivize middle income housing, such as units affordable to residents at 80% of the Area Median Income (AMI) alongside the purely economic incentives for ground floor commercial.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
