<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>40B on Brookline Compliance With The MBTA Community Act</title>
    <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/categories/40b/</link>
    <description>Recent content in 40B on Brookline Compliance With The MBTA Community Act</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/categories/40b/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>What is 40B?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/40b/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/40b/</guid>
      <description>Chapter 40B of the Massachusetts General Law allows builders to bypass local zoning laws to create affordable housing in cities and town that do not meet a certain threshold.
For Brookline, the threshold is met when 10% of our housing is part of our Subsidized Housing Inventory maintained by the state.
40B Project</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is a 40B project?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/40b-project/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/40b-project/</guid>
      <description>A 40B project is a building that is permitted to be built according to Chapter 40B of the Massachusetts General Laws.
Chapter 40B projects are limited in how profitable they can be. However, 40B buildings can compensate for those limits by being larger than projects that follow local zoning laws.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What’s wrong with all of the 40B projects that are happening?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/40b-project-problems/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/40b-project-problems/</guid>
      <description>Developers of buildings use Chapter 40B to bypass town zoning by-laws. As a result, the town cannot ensure that such projects fit into their neighborhoods according to the wishes of the community.
What is Chapter 40B?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How can we prevent being forced to accept 40B projects?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/40b-project-threshold/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/40b-project-threshold/</guid>
      <description>Brookline can reject 40B applications from developers when the subsidized housing inventory of Brookline is above 10% of the total housing stock. When Brookline&amp;rsquo;s subsidized housing inventory is above that threshold, developers can not appeal such rejections.
Thus, to prevent us from bring forced to accept 40B projects, we would have to build or permit housing units that become part of our subsidized housing inventory to stay over the threshold.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>If we only change our zoning to comply with the MBTA-CA without incentivizing more housing, will we still be forced to accept 40B projects?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/mbtaca-40b-impact/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/mbtaca-40b-impact/</guid>
      <description>With our current zoning by-laws, the planning department projects that Brookline will fall below the 10% threshold for being able to reject 40B applications in September, 2023.
By implementing the Harvard Street Study, new developments on Harvard St will all be four story projects with 15% affordable units. This increases both the Numerator and the Denominator of the ratio used to determine if we have enough affordable housing to be able to reject Chapter 40B applications.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
