<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Compliance on Brookline Compliance With The MBTA Community Act</title>
    <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/categories/compliance/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Compliance on Brookline Compliance With The MBTA Community Act</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/categories/compliance/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>What are the requirements that Brookline zoning by-laws must meet to be compliant with the MBTA-CA?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/brookline-zoning-by-law-requirements/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/brookline-zoning-by-law-requirements/</guid>
      <description>Brookline must designate a land area of at least 41 acres that allow multi-family housing by right, known as its &amp;ldquo;multi-family zoning district&amp;rdquo;. The district must have a theoretical capacity of 6,990 units of housing.
At least 50% of the district must be comprised of contiguous lots. Each part of the district must be at least 5 acres of contiguous lots.
90% of the district must be within 0.5 miles of an MBTA subway station, commuter rail station, ferry terminal or bus station.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is the town doing to comply with the MBTA-CA?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/mbtaca-compliance-activity/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/mbtaca-compliance-activity/</guid>
      <description>The town is proceeding in two ways:
The Planning department is developing a zoning update for Harvard Street. The Select Board has charged the MBTA-CA Multifamily Permitting Committee with exploring other options. The Planning Department&#39;s web page devoted to this project answers this question in detail.
What does the MBTA-CA require that the Town of Brookline do?
What goals does the town have besides compliance with the MBTA-CA?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What goals does the town have besides compliance with the MBTA-CA?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/goals-of-the-town/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/goals-of-the-town/</guid>
      <description>The following Goals of the Town were approved in a Select Board Resolution on February 7, 2023.
Protect and expand Commercial uses and commercial tax base Increase net amount of nonluxury housing suitable for all stages of life Facilitate racial, ethnic, income diversity The number of units likely to be built in the multi-family zoning district should be at least 699 units. That is 10% of the capacity required to comply with the MBTA-CA.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Where does the goal for the number of likely units come from?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/town-likely-to-build-housing-goal/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/town-likely-to-build-housing-goal/</guid>
      <description>The MBTA Community Act does not require any housing to be built. It only requires zoning to allow sufficient multi-family housing in a compliant zoning district.
However, the Select Board’s charge to the MBTA-CA Multifamily Permitting Committee includes developing a plan to create at least 699 units, 10% of the total capacity required in Brookline’s MBTA-CA compliant zoning district.
How many units of housing will be incentivized by the Harvard St plan?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What’s wrong with our current zoning code aside from a lack of compliance with MBTA-CA?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/current-zoning-bylaw-problems/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/current-zoning-bylaw-problems/</guid>
      <description>Our current zoning code frequently using FAR to determine the maximum size of a building on a lot. However, using the FAR doesn&amp;rsquo;t lead to predictable outcomes for the form of a building.
The extensive use of special permits in our zoning code make developing housing more expensive because the permitting process takes longer.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How would we integrate some elements of the Harvard St study into any proposal that was developed by the Select Board Multifamily Planning Committee?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/harvard-study/integrating-into-other-plans/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/harvard-study/integrating-into-other-plans/</guid>
      <description>Who would be responsible for that integration?
This isn&amp;rsquo;t part of the remit of the Harvard Street Proposal for MBTA Compliance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What happens if Brookline fails to comply with the MBTA-CA?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/failure-to-comply/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/failure-to-comply/</guid>
      <description>The Attorney General has stated publicly that towns that do not comply with the MBTA, in addition to losing access to state funding for public housing, will be sued by the state.
According to my conversations with the Town Counsel the following would likely occur:
In January, the lawsuit would probably be filed and Brookline would lose through a summary judgement. Brookline would be given a period of time, such as 90 days, to comply.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why shouldn&#39;t communities that are less dense than Brookline have to take a bigger share of the burden?</title>
      <link>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/fair-share-concerns/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://brookline-mbtaca-compliance.great-site.net/posts/fair-share-concerns/</guid>
      <description>Compliance with the MBTA-CA Guidelines uses a theoretical capacity to determine the minimum number of units in a compliant zoning district. This theoretical capacity is calculcated as if each parcel of land has no building on it.
Since Brookline’s compliant zoning district is more likely to have buildings in it already, the burden to build additional housing on Brookline could actually be relatively lower than other, less dense communities.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
